Filipe Alves Cavalcante

Software Engineer

Location: São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil | Phone: +55 11 985346164 | Email: filipe.alvescavalcante@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/cavalcante-filipe | Portfolio: https://filipelab.com

SUMMARY

I am a software engineer focused on the backend with over 6 years of experience in web development. I have worked on a wide range of projects, including PHP, Node.js, Typescript, and frameworks such as Laravel, Express, and NestJS. I also have experience working with the frontend using React and VueJS.

Experience with scaling issues using AWS products such as SQS, DynamoDB, Lambda and also experience integrating with third-party systems such as Stripe, GoogleApi, Amplitude, Google Analytics, etc

SKILLS

Node.js, Nest.js, TypeScript, PHP, Laravel, Vue.js, React, Next.js, JavaScript, MySQL, SQL Server, Postgresql, RESTful, Tailwind, Redis, Azure Cloud, HTML/CSS, Docker, Unit Tests (PHPUnit, Jest), TDD, DDD, Git, Jira/Azure Devops, Postman, Agile Methodologies, SQL Azure, S3, SQS, Azure Storage, Design patterns, SOLID principle, AWS, Lambda, DynamoDB.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer

Gran, Brasilia, BR – Remote

12/2021 to Present

Core Responsibilities:

- Designed and built a new website using React, Next.js and Tailwind to create a more SEO- and performance-focused website for organic growth while still allowing for dynamic changes from a CRM.
- Created and integrated a custom NPM library for React and Next.js components to ensure standardized components and avoid rewriting changes across multiple projects, in addition to contributing to system design.
- Created and integrated RESTful APIs using Laravel and Typescript optimizing communication between microservices and enabling seamless data flow between systems.
- Optimized query performance with indexing strategies and advanced query tuning, reducing latency and improving throughput.
- Contributed to the marketing team by developing promotional banners and landing pages, always optimizing SEO and tracking information.

Key Technologies and Tools: PHP, Laravel, Node.js, Typescript, React, Next.js, SQS, AWS, DynamoDB, Tailwind.

Software Engineer

Gupo Estado, São Paulo, BR - Remote

07/2021 to 12/2021

Core Responsibilities:

- Created and integrated an indexing system with Google API to monitor updates or deletions of news items, avoiding 404 errors and resolving misspelled news tickets.
- Implemented solutions for Google Console errors to improve organic website delivery using PHP and Node.js.
- Designed and built TypeScript bots to purchase products each time deployments were made and uploaded photos to an S3 bucket.

• Worked on war room calls for quick resolutions across the company's systems.

Key Technologies and Tools: PHP, Laravel, Node.js, Typescript, React, Google API, Java, SOLID, PHPUnit

Software Engineer

Gênesis Tecnologia e Inovação, São Paulo, BR - Remote

12/2020 to 07/2021

Core Responsibilities:

- I designed and built endpoints in Laravel with TDD and unit tests, achieving 80% code coverage.
- Optimized query performance with indexing strategies and advanced query adjustments, reducing latency and improving response time.
- Optimized system performance by using cron jobs, reducing server costs by over 15% by distributing them to less busy times, and making the system faster.
- Contributed to the database team by creating and designing the entire database and table relationships.
- Integrated with third-party systems to obtain information and generate additional information for monthly reports, saving one week of work.

Key Technologies and Tools: PHPUnit, Laravel, TDD, UnitTests, Node.js, Postgresql.

Software Engineer

Olivas Digital, São Paulo, BR - Remote

04/2019 to 12/2020

Core Responsibilities:

- Designed and developed a system for global gym equipment vendors with currency conversion integrations, sales order generation integrations, and sales commission reporting.
- Implemented integrations with third-party anti-fraud systems, resulting in an 80% reduction in refounds and a 30% increase in revenue.
- Contributed to all types of projects, such as React Native, React, Laravel, Slim, and WordPress, with very tight deadlines and highly dynamic workloads due to working at a marketing agency.
- Designed and built an automated customer onboarding system for a subscription CRM system.
- Designed and built CI/CD pipelines, reducing deployment errors to almost zero.

Key Technologies and Tools: React Native, React, Laravel, Slim, WordPress, AWS, Azure, PHP, Typescript, MySQL.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of System Analysis and Development

Instituto Federal de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil

03/2016 to Not finished

Associate Degrees IT Technician

Senac, São Paulo, Brazil

06/2013 to 07/2015

CERTIFICATES/COURSES

Clean Code e Clean Architecture, Branas, Brazil GoStack, Rocketseat, Brazil

07/2024

10/2020

LANGUAGES

Portuguese: Native.

English: B2.